that addle the cricket's brain, causing it to behave erratically. When the cricket nears a body of water, such as this swimming pool, it jumps in and drowns, and the worm wriggles out of its suicidal corpse. Crickets are really roomy. Who knew? The tapeworm and the Gordian worm are not alone. They are part of an entire cavalcade of mind-controlling parasites, of fungi, viruses, and worms and insects and more that all specialize in subverting and overriding the wills of their hosts. Now, I first learned about this way of life through David Attenborough's "Trials of Life" about 20 years ago, and then later through a wonderful book called "Parasite Rex" by my friend Carl Zimmer. And I've been writing about these creatures ever since. Few topics in biology enthrall me more. It's like the parasites have subverted my own brain. Because after all, they are always compelling and they are delightfully macabre. When you write about parasites, your lexicon swells with phrases like "devoured alive" and "bursts out of its body." (Laughter) But there's more to it than that. I'm a writer, and fellow writers in the audience will know that we love stories. Parasites invite us to resist the allure of obvious stories. Their world is one of plot twists and unexpected explanations. Why, for example, does this caterpillar start violently thrashing about when another insect gets close to it and those white cocoons that it seems to be standing guard over? Is it maybe protecting its siblings? No. This caterpillar was attacked by a parasitic wasp which laid eggs inside it. The eggs hatched and the young wasps devoured the caterpillar alive before bursting out of its body. See what I mean? Now, the caterpillar didn't die. Some of the wasps seemed to stay behind and controlled it into defending their siblings which are metamorphosing into adults within those cocoons. This caterpillar is a head-banging zombie bodyguard defending the offspring of the creature that killed it. (Applause) We have a lot to get through. I only have 13 minutes. (Laughter) Now, some of you are probably just desperately clawing for some solace in the idea that these things are oddities of the natural world, that they are outliers, and that point of view is understandable, because by their nature, parasites are quite small and they spend a lot of their time inside the bodies of other things. They're easy to overlook, but that doesn't mean that they aren't important. A few years back, a man called Kevin Lafferty took a group of scientists into three Californian estuaries and they pretty much weighed and dissected and recorded everything they could find, and what they found were parasites in extreme abundance. Especially common were trematodes, tiny worms that specialize in castrating their hosts like this unfortunate snail. Now, a single trematode is tiny, microscopic, but collectively they weighed as much as all the fish in the estuaries and three to nine times more than all the birds. And remember the Gordian worm that I showed you, the cricket thing? One Japanese scientist called Takuya Sato found that in one stream, these things drive so many crickets and grasshoppers into the water that the drowned insects make up some 60 percent of the diet of local trout. Manipulation is not an oddity. It is a critical and common part of the world around us, and scientists have now found hundreds of examples of such manipulators, and more excitingly, they're starting to understand exactly how these creatures control their hosts. And this is one of my favorite examples. This is Ampulex compressa, the emerald cockroach wasp, and it is a truth universally acknowledged that an emerald cockroach wasp in possession of some fertilized eggs must be in want of a cockroach. When she finds one, she stabs it with a stinger that is also a sense organ. This discovery came out three weeks ago. She stabs it with a stinger that is a sense organ equipped with small sensory bumps that allow her to feel the distinctive texture of a roach's brain. So like a person blindly rooting about in a bag, she finds the brain, and she injects it with venom into two very specific clusters of neurons. Israeli scientists Frederic Libersat and Ram Gal found that the venom is a very specific chemical weapon. It doesn't kill the roach, nor does it sedate it. The roach could walk away or fly or run if it chose to, but it doesn't choose to, because the venom nixes its motivation to walk, and only that. The wasp basically un-checks the escape-from-danger box in the roach's operating system, allowing her to lead her helpless victim back to her lair by its antennae like a person walking a dog. And once there, she lays an egg on it, egg hatches, devoured alive, bursts out of body, yadda yadda yadda, you know the drill. (Laughter) (Applause) Now I would argue that, once stung, the cockroach isn't a roach anymore. It's more of an extension of the wasp, just like the cricket was an extension of the Gordian worm. These hosts won't get to survive or reproduce. They have as much control over their own fates as my car. Once the parasites get in, the hosts don't get a say. Now humans, of course, are no stranger to manipulation. We take drugs to shift the chemistries of our brains and to change our moods, and what are arguments or advertising or big ideas if not an attempt to influence someone else's mind? But our attempts at doing this are crude and blundering compared to the fine-grained specificity of the parasites. Don Draper only wishes he was as elegant and precise as the emerald cockroach wasp. Now, I think this is part of what makes parasites so sinister and so compelling. We place such a premium on our free will and our independence that the prospect of losing those qualities to forces unseen informs many of our deepest societal fears. Orwellian dystopias and shadowy cabals and mind-controlling supervillains -- these are tropes that fill our darkest fiction, but in nature, they happen all the time. Which leads me to an obvious and disquieting question: Are there dark, sinister parasites that are influencing our behavior without us knowing about it, besides the NSA? If there are any — (Laughter) (Applause) I've got a red dot on my forehead now, don't I? (Laughter) If there are any, this is a good candidate for them. This is Toxoplasma gondii, or Toxo, for short, because the terrifying creature always deserves a cute nickname. Toxo infects mammals, a wide variety of mammals, but it can only sexually reproduce in a cat. And scientists like Joanne Webster have shown that if Toxo gets into a rat or a mouse, it turns the rodent into a cat-seeking missile. If the infected rat smells the delightful odor of cat piss, it runs towards the source of the smell rather than the more sensible direction of away. The cat eats the rat. Toxo gets to have sex. It's a classic tale of Eat, Prey, Love. (Laughter) (Applause) You're very charitable, generous people. Hi, Elizabeth, I loved your talk. How does the parasite control its host in this way? We don't really know. We know that Toxo releases an enzyme that makes dopamine, a substance involved in reward and motivation. We know it targets certain parts of a rodent's brain, including those involved in sexual arousal. But how those puzzle pieces fit together is not immediately clear. What is clear is that this thing is a single cell. This has no nervous system. It has no consciousness. It doesn't even have a body. But it's manipulating a mammal? We are mammals. We are more intelligent than a mere rat, to be sure, but our brains have the same basic structure, the same types of cells, the same chemicals running through them, and the same parasites. Estimates vary a lot, but some figures suggest that one in three people around the world have Toxo in their brains. Now typically, this doesn't lead to any overt illness. The parasite holds up in a dormant state for a long period of time. But there's some evidence that those people who are carriers score slightly differently on personality questionnaires than other people, that they have a slightly higher risk of car accidents, and there's some evidence that people with schizophrenia are more likely to be infected. Now, I think this evidence is still inconclusive, and even among Toxo researchers, opinion is divided as to whether the parasite is truly influencing our behavior. But given the widespread nature of such manipulations, it would be completely implausible for humans to be the only species that weren't similarly affected. And I think that this capacity to constantly subvert our way of thinking about the world makes parasites amazing. They're constantly inviting us to look at the natural world sideways, and to ask if the behaviors we're seeing, whether they're simple and obvious or baffling and puzzling, are not the results of individuals acting through their own accord but because they are being bent to the control of something else. And while that idea may be disquieting, and while parasites' habits may be very grisly, I think that ability to surprise us makes them as wonderful and as charismatic as any panda or butterfly or dolphin. At the end of "On the Origin of Species," Charles Darwin writes about the grandeur of life, and of endless forms most beautiful and most wonderful, and I like to think he could easily have been talking about a tapeworm that makes shrimp sociable or a wasp that takes cockroaches for walks. But perhaps, that's just a parasite talking. Thank you. (Applause)
que confunden al cerebro del grillo haciendo que se comporte de forma errática. Cuando el grillo se acerca a un cuerpo de agua, como esta piscina, salta y se ahoga, y el gusano se escape del cadáver suicida. Los grillos son muy espaciosos. ¿Quién lo hubiera imaginado? La tenia y el gusano gordiano no están solos. Son parte de toda una cabalgata de parásitos que controlan la mente, de los hongos, los virus y los gusanos e insectos y más que todos se especializan en subvertir y reemplazar las voluntades de sus anfitriones. Ahora, me enteré de esta forma de vida a través de "La vida a prueba" de David Attenborough hace unos 20 años y más tarde a través de un libro maravilloso llamado "Parasite Rex" de mi amigo Carl Zimmer. Y he estado escribiendo acerca de estas criaturas desde entonces. Pocos temas en la biología me cautivan más. Es como si los parásitos hubiesen trastornado mi propio cerebro. Porque después de todo, ellos siempre son convincentes y son deliciosamente macabros. Cuando se escribe sobre los parásitos, el léxico se incrementa con frases como "devorado vivo" y "estalla de su cuerpo". (Risas) Pero hay más que eso. Soy un escritor y los colegas escritores en la audiencia sabrán que amamos las historias. Los parásitos nos invitan a resistirnos a la atracción de las historias obvias. Su mundo es de giros en la trama y de explicaciones inesperadas. ¿Por qué, por ejemplo, esta oruga empieza a golpear violentamente cuando otro insecto se acerca a ella y a esos capullos blancos que parece que les está haciendo guardia? ¿Es tal vez la protección de sus hermanos? No. Esta oruga fue atacada por una avispa parásita que puso huevos en su interior. Los huevos eclosionaron y las jóvenes avispas devoraron la oruga viva antes de estallar fuera de su cuerpo. ¿Ven lo que quiero decir? Ahora, la oruga no murió. Algunas de las avispas parecían haberse quedado y la controlan en defensa de sus hermanos que se metamorfosean en los adultos dentro de los capullos. Esta oruga es un zombi guardaespaldas que se golpea la cabeza en defensa de las crías de la criatura que la mataron. (Aplausos) Tenemos mucho para repasar. Solo tengo 13 minutos. (Risas) Ahora, algunos de Uds. probablemente arañan desesperadamente un poco de consuelo en la idea de que estas cosas son rarezas del mundo natural, que son extrañezas, y ese punto de vista es comprensible, porque por su naturaleza, los parásitos son bastante pequeños y pasan mucho de su tiempo dentro de los cuerpos de otras cosas. Son fáciles de pasar por alto, pero eso no quiere decir que no sean importantes. Hace unos años, un hombre llamado Kevin Lafferty llevó a un grupo de científicos dentro de tres estuarios de California y prácticamente pesaron y diseccionaron y grabaron todo lo que pudieron encontrar y lo que encontraron fue parásitos en abundancia extrema. Especialmente comunes fueron los trematodos, pequeños gusanos que se especializan en castrar a sus anfitriones como este desafortunado caracol. Ahora, un único trematodo es pequeño, microscópico, pero en conjunto pesaron tanto como todos los peces en los estuarios y tres a nueve veces más que todos los pájaros. ¿Y recuerdan el gusano gordiano que les mostré, el grillo? Un científico japonés llamado Takuya Sato encontró que en una sola corriente, estas cosas conducen tantos grillos y langostas al agua que los insectos ahogados constituyen alrededor del 60 % de la dieta de la trucha local. La manipulación no es una rareza. Es una parte crítica y común del mundo que nos rodea, y los científicos han descubierto ahora cientos de ejemplos de tales manipuladores, y más emocionante, están empezando a entender exactamente cómo estas criaturas controlan a sus huéspedes. Este es uno de mis ejemplos favoritos. Este es Ampulex compressa, la avispa esmeralda cucaracha, y es una verdad universalmente reconocida que una cucaracha avispa esmeralda en posesión de algunos huevos fertilizados necesita a una cucaracha. Cuando encuentra una, la apuñala con un aguijón que también es un órgano sensorial. Este descubrimiento salió hace tres semanas. Ella apuñala con un aguijón que es un órgano de los sentidos equipado con pequeñas protuberancias sensoriales que le permiten sentir la textura distintiva del cerebro de una cucaracha. Así como una persona enraíza ciegamente en una bolsa, ella encuentra el cerebro, y le inyecta un veneno en dos grupos muy específicos de neuronas. Los científicos israelíes Frederic Libersat y Ram Gal encontraron que el veneno es un arma química muy específica. No mata a la cucaracha, ni la seda. La cucaracha podría alejarse o volar o correr si lo decidiera, pero no lo hace, debido a que el veneno inhibe su motivación para caminar y solo eso. La avispa básicamente desmarca la casilla de escape-del-peligro en el sistema operativo de la cucaracha, lo que le permite llevar a su víctima indefensa de vuelta a su guarida por sus antenas como una persona que pasea un perro. Y una vez allí, pone un huevo en ella, el huevo eclosiona, devorándola viva, estalla fuera del cuerpo, ta ta ta, conocen el ejercicio. (Risas) (Aplausos) Ahora yo diría que, una vez picada, la cucaracha no es una cucaracha más. Es más bien una extensión de la avispa, al igual que el grillo era una extensión del gusano gordiano. Estos anfitriones no conseguirán sobrevivir o reproducirse. Ellos tienen tanto control sobre su propio destino como mi coche. Una vez que los parásitos entran, los anfitriones no tienen voz. Ahora los seres humanos, por supuesto, no son ajenos a la manipulación. Tomamos drogas para cambiar la química de nuestro cerebro y para cambiar nuestro estado de ánimo, y ¿qué son los argumentos o la publicidad o las grandes ideas si no un intento de influir en la mente de otra persona? Pero nuestros intentos de hacer esto son crudos y torpes en comparación a la especificidad de grano fino de los parásitos. Don Draper solo desea que él fuera tan elegante y preciso como la avispa esmeralda cucaracha. Ahora, creo que esto es parte de lo que hace a los parásitos tan siniestros y tan convincentes. Damos tanto valor a nuestro libre albedrío y nuestra independencia que la posibilidad de perder esas cualidades por fuerzas invisibles sustenta muchos de nuestros temores sociales más profundos. Distopías orwellianas y cábalas sombrías y supervillanos que controlan la mente, estos son los tropos que llenan nuestra ficción más oscura, pero en la naturaleza, ocurre todo el tiempo. Lo que me lleva a una evidente e inquietante pregunta: ¿Hay oscuros parásitos siniestros influyendo en nuestro comportamiento sin que sepamos de ellos, además de la NSA? Si hay alguno... (Risas) (Aplausos) Tengo un punto rojo en la frente, ¿cierto? (Risas) Si los hay, este es un buen candidato para ello. Este es el Toxoplasma gondii, o Toxo, para abreviar, porque la criatura terrorífica siempre merece un apodo lindo. Toxo infecta a los mamíferos, a una amplia variedad de mamíferos, pero solo puede reproducirse sexualmente en un gato. Y los científicos como Joanne Webster han demostrado que si Toxo entra en una rata o un ratón, este se convierte en un misil roedor en busca de gatos. Si la rata infectada huele el olor delicioso de la orina de gato, corre hacia la fuente del olor en lugar de la dirección apropiada de alejarse. El gato se come la rata. Toxo tiene relaciones sexuales. Es el cuento clásico de la Comer, Rezar, Amar. (Risas) (Aplausos) Uds. son personas generosas, caritativas. Hola, Elizabeth, me encantó tu charla. ¿Cómo controla el parásito a su huésped de esta manera? En realidad no lo sabemos. Sabemos que Toxo libera una enzima que produce dopamina, una sustancia involucrada en la recompensa y la motivación. Sabemos que se dirige a ciertas partes del cerebro de un roedor, incluyendo aquellos involucrados en la excitación sexual. Pero ¿cómo las piezas del rompecabezas encajan entre sí, no está claro de momento. Lo que está claro es que esta cosa es una sola célula. No tiene sistema nervioso. No tiene consciencia. Ni siquiera tiene un cuerpo. Pero ¿está manipulando un mamífero? Somos mamíferos. Somos más inteligentes que una simple rata, seguro, pero nuestros cerebros tienen la misma estructura básica, los mismos tipos de células, las mismas sustancias químicas que circulan en sus cuerpos y los mismos parásitos. Las estimaciones varían mucho, pero algunos datos sugieren que una de cada tres personas en todo el mundo tienen Toxo en sus cerebros. Ahora normalmente, esto no conduce a ninguna enfermedad manifiesta. El parásito se mantiene en un estado latente durante un largo período. Pero hay alguna evidencia de que las personas que son portadoras tienen una puntuación ligeramente diferente en cuestionarios de personalidad que las demás personas, que tienen un riesgo ligeramente más alto de accidentes de tráfico, y hay alguna evidencia de que las personas con esquizofrenia son más propensas a ser infectadas. Ahora, creo que esta evidencia aún no es concluyente, e incluso entre Toxo investigadores, las opiniones están divididas en cuanto a si el parásito está influyendo verdaderamente nuestro comportamiento. Pero dada la naturaleza generalizada de esas manipulaciones, sería completamente inverosímil que los seres humanos seamos la única especie que no se vean afectados de forma similar. Y creo que esta capacidad de trastornar constantemente nuestra forma de pensar acerca del mundo hace increíbles a los parásitos. Constantemente nos invitan a soslayar al mundo natural y a preguntar si los comportamientos que estamos viendo, son simples y obvios o desconcertantes y enigmáticos, si no son el resultado de los individuos actuando a través de su propia voluntad pero debido a que se están sujetos al control de algo más. Y aunque esa idea puede ser inquietante y aunque los hábitos de los parásitos pueden ser muy espantosos, creo que la capacidad de sorprendernos los hace tan maravillosos y tan carismáticos como cualquier panda o mariposa o delfín. Al final de "El Origen de las Especies", Charles Darwin escribe acerca de la grandeza de la vida, y de infinidad de formas muy bellas y de lo más maravillosas y me gusta pensar que podría fácilmente haber estado hablando sobre una tenia que hace que al camarón sociable o una avispa que se lleva a las cucarachas para pasear. Pero tal vez, eso es solo una conversación de parásito. Gracias. (Aplausos)